The Marie Corelli Collection
Yale University Music Library
The Marie Corelli Collection
1880-1927
MSS 19
Yale University Music Library
0.5
(1 box)
Manuscript scores of songs composed by or otherwise connected to the British author and musician Marie Corelli (1855-1924)
Corelli, Marie, 1855-1924
Conditions Governing Access
The Collection is open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Arrangement
In 4 series as follows: I. Songs composed by Marie Corelli. II. Songs by various composers to texts by Marie Corelli. III. Songs dedicated to or presentation copies given by composers to Marie Corelli. IV. Miscellaneous materials.
Scope and Contents
The Marie Corelli Collection contains manuscript scores of songs composed by Corelli. The Collection also includes: songs composed by other composers to texts by Corelli; an autograph letter to Corelli from Frank Dixon; and presentation copies of songs by various composers.
Biographical / Historical
Mary Mackay, who is known by the pseudonym Marie Corelli, was born in London in 1855. Her parentage is uncertain, but it has been argued that her adoptive father, the poet and song writer Charles Mackay, was her biological father as well. She was trained in music, and in 1884 made her debut as an improvisational pianist, but her musical career was short-lived. Corelli achieved far greater success as a writer; her novels, many of which deal with spiritualism, were extraordinarily popular in the late 19th and early 20th centuries, although they received little critical acclaim. She died in 1924.
Songs; Bal, Henriette; Corelli, Marie, 1855-1924; Davy, Francis Arthur; Dixon, Frank; Greene, Edwin, 1856-1915; Hare, Amy; Haydon, Claude M. (Claude Meurisse), 1884-1960; Henderson, Walter; Kyrle, Marion; Martin, Easthope, 1882-1925; Ravall, J. H.; St. Clair, Humphrey; Thiele, Fritz; Tosti, F. Paolo (Francesco Paolo), 1846-1916; West, Edmund; Wilmont, Aubrey; Wilson, H. Chilver; Woodforde-Finden, Amy, 1860-1919
- Songs composed by Marie Corelli, Series I
  - Great-Grandfather, poetry by Charles MacKay, L.L.D., 8 p. 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General
    Holograph in ink.
    Corrections and additional marks in pencil and blue crayon.
    For voice and piano.
    2 copies.
  - Juanita. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    See Near Thee, Near Thee, Ever Near Thee.
  - Love Me Little, Love Me Long., 7 p. 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Holograph in ink, over pencil.
  - A Most Sweet Lady! / Song / Words and Music / by / Marie Corelli., 5 p. 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Corrections and additions in pencil.
    Presentation copy to Mrs. G.H. Wilder with the composer's autograph.
    3 copies.
  - [My sweet sweeting] Dedicated / by Permission / to / Edward Lloyd / My Sweet Sweeting / Song / The poetry by / King Henry VIII / Music by / Marie Corelli., 5 p. 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Markings and corrections by the composer.
    Holograph signed by the composer.
  - My Sweet Sweeting. London, Laudy & Co., no date, 7 p. 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Near Thee, Near Thee, Ever Near Thee. Juanita., 7 p. 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - [Romeo's good night] Dedicated by Permission / to / Henry Irving / Romeo's Good Night / Words from / Shakespeare / The Music by / M. Corelli., 7 p. 30 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Presentation copy to Bertha Vyver with the composer's autograph.
    Markings in pencil.
  - Romeo's Good Night. London, Stanley Lucas, Weber & Co., no date, 6 p. 36 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Imperfect copy.
- Songs by various composers to texts by Marie Corelli, Series II
  - Last Love Song, poetry from Marie Corelli's "Sorrows of Satan"., Bal, Henriette; 2 p. 33 cm. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Presentation copy to Marie Corelli with the composer'autograph.
  - Nocturne / by / Chopin / "The Voice in the Cathedral" / Words by / Marie Corelli / arranged / for soprano and piano / by / L. Emil-Bach., Chopin, Frédéric, 1810-1849; 6 p. 36 cm. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Manuscript in ink.
    Corrections in pencil by arranger.
  - If I Loved You! London, F.A. Davy, c1902., Davy, F.A., Lt. Col.; 6 p. 37 cm. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    2 copies, No. 1 presentation copy to Marie Corelli with the composer's autograph.
  - The Lotus Lily. London, Novello & Co., c1902., Davy, F.A., Lt. Col.; 4 p. 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Here by the Sea /words by / Marie Corelli / the "Temporal Power" / Music by / Frank Dixon / Dec. 1902., Dixon, Frank; 4 p. 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Holograph in purple pencil.
  - Coronation. London, Frederick Harris Co., c1927., Hare, Amy; 6 p. 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - A Love Song. Londonp Frederick Harris & Co., c1927., Hare, Amy; 4 p. 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Presentation copy to Marie Corelli with the composer's autograph.
  - O Love, my Love / words by Marie Corelli / Music by Claude M. Haydon / Melbourne, 19th March, 1907., Haydon, Claude M. (Claude Meurisse), 1884-1960; 6 p. 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Holograph in ink, with red ink underlinings.
  - Ziska: Danse Caracteristique. London, W. Henderson, no date, Henderson, Walter; score (7 p.) and part 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Corrections in ink.
    For mandoline solo and keyboard accompaniment.
  - Here, by the Sea, words from Marie Corelli's "Temporal Power"., Kyrle, Marion; 4 p. 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Lotus-Lily, words from Marie Corelli's "Ziska"., Martin, F.J. Easthope; 3 p. 27 x 36 cm. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Holograph in ink; at end: F.J.E.M.,
  - The Lotus-Lily. London, Metzler & Co., Ltd., c1907., Martin, F.J. Easthope; 4 p. 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Presentation copy to Marie Corelli with the comooser's autograph.
    Markings in ink.
  - The Lord is my Shepherd., Ravall, J. H.; 1 leaf 17 x 24 cm. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Copyist's [Marie Corelli?] manuscript in ink.
  - The Lord is my Shepherd., [Author unknown]; 1 leaf 27 cm. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Manuscript copy in ink.
    For 4 parts with keyboard accompaniment.
  - Prayer / Words by Miss Marie Corelli / Song for one contralto voice / with accompaniment of the piano or the organ / by / Fritz Thiele., Thiele, Fritz; 4 p. 27 cm. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    For voice and keyboard accompaniment.
  - I Dare To Love Thee. London, Chappell & Co., no date, Tosti, F. Paolo (Francesco Paolo), 1846-1916; 7 p. 36 cm. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Song of the Lotus-Lily. London, Robert Cocks Co., c1898., Ward, Amy; 7 p. 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Fidelity. London, J.B. Cramer & Co., Ltd., c1908., West, Edmund; 5 p. 36 cm. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - O Wild World! / Words by / Marie Corelli / Music by / Aubrey C. Wilmont / with violin obligato ad lib., Wilmont, Aubrey C.; 2 p. 30 cm. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Holograph in ink; at end: 1904.
    Signed by the composer.
  - Let Me Be Thine. London, John Church & Co., c1903., Wilson, H. Chilver; 5 p. 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Songs dedicated to or presentation copies given by composers to Marie Corelli, Series III
  - [A Tale of Old Japan. Piano-vocal score. English] A Tale of Old Japan; a cantata for soli, chorus and orchestra. The poem by Alfred Noyes. The music by S. Coleridge-Taylor. London, Novello; New York: H.W. Gray, sole agents for the U.S.A., c1911., Coleridge, Samuel Taylor, 1772-1834; 99 p. 26 cm. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Presentation copy to Marie Corelli by the Stratford on Avon Choral and Orchestral Society.
  - The Gilded Popinjay. London, Phillips & Page, c1909., Greene, Edwin, 1856-1915; 7 p. 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - The Music That Came With May. London, Phillips & Page, c1904., Greene, Edwin, 1856-1915; 7 p. 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Presentation copy to Marie Corelli with composer's autograph.
  - To My Love. London, Phillips & Page, c1909., Greene, Edwin, 1856-1915; 7 p. 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - The Fleeting Years. London, Phillips & Page, c1906., Greene, Edwin, 1856-1915; 7 p. [pp. 3-6 wanting] 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - O-come-to Edin's-Burgh-so clear!, St. Clair, Humphrey; 3 p. 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Holograph in ink; at end: Composed at Edinburgh / Dec. 1st 1910.
- Miscellaneous materials, Series IV
  - Letter to Marie Corelli from Frank Dixon., autograph letter signed, dated February 2, 1903. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Danse Créole. Paris, Enoch & Cie., c1898., Chaminade, Cécile Louise Stéphanie, 1861-1944; 6 p. 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 32)
    For piano.
  - Hochzeitstag auf Troldhaugen. Leipzig, Peters Edition, c1897., Grieg, Edvard, 1843-1907; 11 p. 30 cm. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - La Berceuse - Schlummerlied, [D. 527]., Schubert, Franz, 1797-1828; 1 leaf 30 cm. (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Copyist's [M. Corelli?] manuscript in ink; at end: The 9th of April 77.
    For piano and voice.
  - News. [185-]., Musical Supplement to the Illustrated London; 16 nos. 43 cm. (Box 2, Folder 1)